视频发布于2021年12月13日 发射日期以实际为准
今年的12月21日 将可能改变人类对宇宙的认知
This December, 21st may become known as the day the universe changed.
在那个周三 NASA将要发射詹姆斯·韦伯太空望远镜(JWST)
That Wednesday, NASA expects to launch the James Webb Space Telescope.
人类至今单次发射过的最昂贵的航天器
The largest and most expensive instrument ever flown,
比31岁高龄的哈勃望远镜强一百倍
100 times more powerful than the 31-year-old Hubble telescope,
JWST可以穿越时光 观察宇宙在创世之初的模样
Web can see back in time, all the way to the "let there be light" moment.
那个又冷又黑的早期宇宙迸发出无数恒星的瞬间
That instant when a cold, dark universe ignited into stars.
故事稍后开始
The story will continue in a moment.
哇
Wow.
比我想象中要大多了
Well, somehow that's a lot bigger than I imagine.
一年前 我们成为了少数在JWST上天前最后看了它一眼的人
A year ago, we were among the last humans to see the telescope, much as it will appear in space.
在我们此次来访后 它会被打包装箱 向月球之外的茫茫深空进发
After our visit, it was packed away for a journey of a million miles, far beyond the moon.
永远留在绕日轨道上
To lie forever in the grasp of the sun.
它能在太空运行多久？
The operating life is how long?
设计寿命是5.5年 目标是10年
It's designed for five and a half years, with a goal of ten years.
我们要给它备足干粮 够它用十年的
So that means we carry enough stuff on there to last for ten years.
Amy Lo是一位系统工程师
Amy Lo is a systems engineer,
她带我们来到加州Rhodondo滩诺斯罗普·格鲁曼公司的无尘室内
who took us up in the clean room at Northrop Grumman in Rhodondo Beach, California.
我们发明、设计、制造、纯手工组装
We had invent it, design it, build it, and hand put it together.
望远镜底部的银色薄膜是它的遮阳伞
At the bottom of the spacecraft, that silver shroud is a parasol,
有网球场那么大 为望远镜遮阳
big as a tennis court to shield Web from the sun.
而上面 是21英尺(6.5米)镀金主镜 面积是哈勃望远镜的六倍
Above, there are 21-feet of gold-plated mirrors, 6 times bigger than Hubble's mirror,
用来捕捉宇宙最早期的微弱星光
to catch the earliest starlight in creation.
一共有18块六边形镜面
There were 18 of these hexagonal mirrors.
而当它展开后 它们会变成一整块镜子？
But when you fold them out, they all work in concert as one mirror?
是的 18只眼睛会组合成一幅完美、高清的画面
That's right, all 18 images will form one, very nice, solid image.
而人眼并不能看到组合后的画面
That image would be invisible to the human eye.
类似于夜视相机 JWST设计是观测红外光的
Like a night vision camera, Web is designed to see heat, infrared light.
因为红外线是最早期宇宙留下的唯一痕迹
Because that's the only signature left from the stars at the edge of time.
即便如此 那样的光亮还需要曝光几小时才能获得图像
Even that glow will be so dim, the mirrors will have to squint for hours to expose an image.
您有多大信心？
How much confidence do you have?
呃……为各种事担忧就是我的责任
Errr … You know, My job is to worry.
我个人还是比较有自信的 因为我们已经把能考虑的都考虑到了
I personally feel confident that we have … thought of … everything.
光是这个“考虑” 就花了25年 100亿美元
Thinking of everything took more than 25 years, and 10 billion dollars.
工程师Amy Lo 向大家介绍了具体工程难点
Engineer Amy Lo, explained the challenge.
我个人认为最大的工程难点是遮阳罩的部分
In my mind, the biggest engineering challenge was to build a sun shield,
用来保护光学组件、镜面和望远镜仪器的遮阳罩
capable of shielding the optics, the mirrors and the instrument on Web.
怎样才能把它造得又大又轻？
How do you build something big but light weight?
遮阳罩可以让JWST在暗处保持低温
The sun shield keeps Web cold and dark.
来自太阳和地球的一丝热量都会影响望远镜的红外观测
Any infrared heat from the sun or earth would blind the telescope.
五层遮阳罩薄如蝉翼 和生日宴会气球上的材料完全不同
The 5 layers are made of gossamer sheets, not unlike mylar birthday balloons.
直面太阳照射的那层是第一层
The layer facing the sun is layer one.
温度在230华氏度(110摄氏度)
And layer one reaches about 230°F.
相当于个小烤箱了 煮个茶叶蛋没啥问题
So a pretty warm oven, like if you wanted to cook a morang or something.
那望远镜那一侧呢？
And on the … on the telescope side?
望远镜那一侧 温度低至-370华氏度(-223摄氏度 50开)
On the telescope side, it gets to -370°F.
两边温差有三百多摄氏度……
There's a roughly 600 degree difference …
-没错 -在遮阳罩的两侧？
-There is. -Between one side of the heat shield and the other?
是的 非常厉害 做到这一切 靠的只是这些……
Yes, it's amazing, that it's able to do this with nothing more …
这样的薄膜
than these layers.
望远镜在工程学上已经很强了 但在科学上 它更是能够揭开宇宙的终极奥秘
The engineering is amazing, but the science may reveal the universe.
自大爆炸以来 宇宙已经走过了近140亿年
Since the beginning, the big Bang, the arrow of time has flown nearly 14 billion years.
JWST能够观测到最初一亿年——宇宙最早期的时候
Web may see all the way back to the first 100 million, the baby universe.
Amber Straughn是项目组里的天体物理学家
Amber Straughn is an astrophysicist on the project.
望远镜就是我们的时光机 它能直接看到过去的事物
Telescopes really are time machines, they literally allow us to see into the past.
原因很简单 因为光是有速度的
And the reason for that is just due to the nature of how light travels.
太阳发出的光要八分钟才能到地球
Light from the sun takes about eight minutes to get to the earth.
所以我们眼中的太阳都是八分钟之前的太阳
So we're seeing the sun as it was eight minutes ago.
放眼到整个宇宙 道理也是一样的
And you can sort of think about stepping that further out into the universe.
所以我们在夜里散步 仰望星空之时
So when we walk out under the stars and look above us,
看到的都不是它们“现在”的样子
We're not seeing the stars as they are today.
-我们看到的……可能是它们数百万年前的样子 -没错
-We're seeing them as they were, perhaps millions of years ago. -Absolutely.
-因为光要花那么久才能到达地球 -是的
-Because it took that long for the light to reach the earth. -Yes, for sure.
人类对宇宙了解有多少？
How much do we know about the universe.
从你我在这个星球上观测到的、我们对宇宙的了解
Everything we know about, everything we can see, me and you, everything on the planet,
观测到的上千亿个星系 只占整个宇宙的5%
all the hundreds of billions of other galaxies, all of that only makes up about 5% of the universe,
剩余那95% 我们一无所知
the rest of it, that other 95%, we have no idea what it is.
那95%的未知事物 就像幽灵一样在宇宙中游荡
That 95%, the unknown, is all around us like a ghost.
宇宙几乎都是由物理学家无奈称之为“暗物质”和“暗能量”的东西构成的
Nearly all the cosmos is made up of what physicists call in desperation, dark matter and dark energy.
虽然从未观测到 但科学家推测它们一定是存在的
Never seen, scientists infer they must exist
因为它们是星系构成与移动的最好解释
because they're the best explanation for how galaxies form and move.
因此我们认为暗物质是宇宙的一种“框架”
So we know that dark matter is sort of the scaffolding of the universe.
它是星系所依托的结构
It's the the structure on which galaxies sit.
如果没有暗物质 就不会有星系 更不会有我们
Uh, and if there wasn't dark matter, there wouldn't be galaxies and there wouldn't be us.
JWST能揭示出关于暗物质的哪些内容？
What might the Web telescope reveal about dark matter?
就好像我们面前摆着宇宙140亿年的编年史 但却少了第一章一样
It's like we have this 14-billion-year-old story of the universe, but we're missing that first chapter.
而JWST的设计就是让我们观测到
And Web was specifically designed to allow us to see
大爆炸后最初形成的那些星系
those very first galaxies that formed after the Big Bang.
星系形成后 它们也会演变 会随着时间推移发生变化
Now galaxies are born and then they evolve, they change over time.
而星系的这种演变严重依赖于暗物质的存在
And this way that galaxies change must rely critically on dark matter.
JWST可以让我们更清楚地观测到星系的演变过程
And Web is going to allow us to observe that process of galaxy evolution in much more detail.
载着全村人的希望 JWST的旅程一直都不顺利
The promise of discovery, shielded Web on what's already been a treacherous journey.
它本来在七年前就该发射的 但却一鸽再鸽
It was to launch 7 years ago, but delays come with a machine this ambitious.
由于成本超支 JWST在2011年被众议院拨款委员会取消
Because of cost overruns, Web was cancelled in 2011 by the House Appropriations Committee,
但在参议院被保存了下来
but it was saved in the Senate.
它的名字 詹姆斯·韦伯 是60年代NASA的主管 让科学站上了首位
Its namesake is James Webb, head of NASA in the 1960s, who made science at top priority.
在JWST上你们都押上了什么？
What are the stakes? What's riding on that rocket with Web?
真要说赌注的话 就是NASA执行这个任务的声誉吧
When you talk about what's at stake, it really is NASA's reputation, to take on a mission.
难度高 还没有失败的余地
That is as challenging as Web and be successful.
Bill Oaks和Gregory Robinson负责该项目
Bill Oaks and Gregory Robinson run the program.
Oaks曾是哈勃的工程师 Robinson负责NASA的质量管理
Oaks was an engineer on Hubble, Robinson has supervised NASA Quality and performance.
真想在科学上拿出实打实的成果 就得让他们下血本掏钱
If you want to be bold and get the kind of science way after, you have to make them investment.
而它也会解答两个大问题
And it's going to answer two big questions, faster physics.
我们从哪来 我们是孤独的吗？
Where did we come from, and are we alone?
我们很期待这些方面的答案
We're looking forward to get those results.
JWST会成功吗？
Is Web gonna work?
-会的 我很有自信 -我有百分之百的信心
-Yes, it's gonna work, I have very high confidence. -I am 100% confident.
百分之百？
Why 100% confident?
我看过了这些年他们做过的各种测试
Because when I look at the testing that we have done over the years.
看到了他们在工程学上无所不用其极
And the type of engineering that went into it,
你就会慢慢感觉 这样的项目不成功天理难容
you build a sense of confidence that you know what's going to work.
您现在最担心哪个环节？
What are you most concerned about?
整个望远镜展开的环节吧
Unfolding the entire telescope is what you worry about.
望远镜需要折叠进阿丽亚娜5火箭只有16英尺(5.4米)宽的整流罩内
The observatory had to be folded into an Ariane 5 rocket, just 16-feet wide.
它现在在里面就像花蕾一样
It's wrapped today tight as a rosebud.
发射以后 超过40套系统必须完美“绽放”
In flight, more than 40 systems must blossom with perfection.
包括Amy Lo第一次制造的如此巨大的遮阳罩
Including Amy Lo's never invented before, Sun Shield.
所有五层遮阳罩都要折叠起来
All 5 layers will be folded up.
然后用“图钉”固定起来？一共多少“图钉”啊？
And held in place by "pins"? How many "pins" are there?
五层遮阳罩一共107个遮阳膜释放装置
There's 107 of these membrane released devices and "pins" that hold all 5 layers.
UPS: Unitized Pallet Structure 组合托盘结构
把遮阳罩固定在这部分名为UPS的结构
Pin to this structure here, call the UPS, all Total 107.
那在展开过程中 能允许多少个释放装置失效？
And, as you're unfolding, how many of those can fail?
零
None.
-零？ -零 -一个也不能坏？ -是的
-None? -None -Not one? -Not one.
完全没有出故障的余地
There is literally no room for error.
我们进行了无数次测试与分析来保证
We are test, and we do a lot of analysis to ensure
在太空每一个这样的释放装置都能正常运转
that each and every single one of these will release on orbit.
一百亿美元 就靠这107个“图钉”了
10 billion dollars rides on those pins.
哈勃望远镜在距地面340英里(550公里)的近地轨道上 拿个扳手上去就能修
The Hubble Telescope, 340 miles up, could be reached with a wrench.
但JWST 在一百万英里外(150万公里左右) 谁也修不了
Web, at a million miles, is beyond repair.
Bill Oaks跟我们说 如果展开过程中有卡阻 那么还有一套紧急方案
Bill Oaks told us that if something does get stuck, there is an emergency plan.
我们开发出一套控制算法让望远镜能……自行震动
We've developed algorithms to essentially, may, we call it the shimmy,
给望远镜引入一个小震动 让它前后摆动
we do a little shake on a telescope and we can rock it back and forth.
要是还不行 我们还能让它自传
That doesn't work. We have one we call the "twirl",
让望远镜原地顺时针逆时针转 看能不能把东西晃松开
which can actually spin the telescope be the clockwise or counterclockwise, to help shake things loose.
就像老百姓手里啥玩意不好使了就使劲晃晃？
So you're gonna do what I do with devices when they're not working, you're going to shake it.
对 对 差不多意思
Yeah, yeah, can I do the same thing? Yes.
107个释放装置展开、镜面展开、其他上万个动作正常部署
If 107 pins release, the mirror synchronize and 10000 things go right,
JWST携带的用于维持轨道与姿态的燃料也只够用十年
Web will be limited only by about ten years of fuel for pivoting and pointing.
加拿大负责了望远镜的瞄准系统 能让它凝视宇宙深处
Canada contributed the aiming system that will guide Web to wonders far and near.
上千位天文学家都在争取望远镜的观测时间
More than a thousand astronomers around the world are competing for telescope time.
Heidi Hamill获得了100小时的观测时间
Heidi Hamill was granted one hundred hours.
我有一肚子问题想问 我的专业方向主要在我们太阳系内
I have so many questions, my particular focus is objects in our solar system.
Hamill告诉大家 光其实充满了各种信息
Hamill told us that light is full of information.
JWST可以分析光的波长来判断存在的化学物质
Web can define the chemistry of a place by analyzing its wavelengths of light.
火星大气中的水含量是多少 它是如何随时间变化的？
What is the atmospheric water content of Mars, and how does it change with time?
是什么驱动了海王星上层大气的化学变化？
What drives the chemistry in the upper atmosphere of Neptune?
我们能否在木星或土星的卫星上发现水的存在？
Can we see if there's water coming out of the moons of Jupiter or Saturn?
无数问题我都想知道答案
There are just infinite number of questions I want to answer.
天体物理学家Natalie Batalha也争取到了观测时间
Astrophysicist Natalie Batalha also has time on Web.
她将关注太阳系外的行星
She'll be looking at planets beyond our solar system.
平均下来 银河系里每个恒星都至少有一个行星
On average, every star in the galaxy has at least one planet.
也就是说银河系里行星的数量比恒星还多
That means that there are more planets in the galaxy than there are stars.
上千亿颗星球
Hundreds of billions of planets.
有了这么多行星
And with that many planets,
Batalha相信JWST可以找到一些拥有适宜生命存在的化学物质与环境的星球
Batalha is sure Web could find some with the chemistry and conditions of life.
恰好有那么一个恒星 有七颗行星围绕它运行
There happens to be one planetary system, the star has seven planets orbiting it.
应该指的是TRAPPIST-1星系
而这个恒星离我们只有40光年
And the star is only about 40 light years away.
是一个极好的研究目标 拥有三个地球大小的行星环绕
So it's a great target to study, and it has three earth size planets orbiting
而且这三颗行星都在适居带上 也就是可能存在生命的地方
in what I would call the Goldilocks zone, where life could potentially exist.
-不太冷也不太热 -没错
-Not too hot, not too cold. -That's the idea, yes.
因此它是我们要用JWST观察的第一批目标之一
And so this is also one of the very first targets that we're going to observe, observe with Web.
我们能够观测的是大气中的二氧化碳
And what will be able to to see is … is their carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.
他们的温室气体是什么？是与甲烷结合在一起的二氧化碳吗？
What are the greenhouse gases? Is their carbon dioxide in combination with methane?
因为地球就是如此
Because that's what earth has.
因此通过观察这些化学成分 我们也许能够拼凑出一个结果
So by looking at these chemical constituents, we might be able to piece together,
从而了解到它到底只是一颗位于适居带的行星 还是拥有真正的宜居环境
if it's not just a planet in what we call the habitable zone, but if it's truly a habitable environment.
有人可能会问 这有什么好观测的？
And somebody might ask, why does it matter?
而这的最终目的是想确认我们在宇宙中到底是不是孤独的
The end point is to … put an end to our cosmic loneliness.
我们想知道到底有没有地外生命
We want to know if there's life out there.
您作为研究者的角度来看 JWST是创新还是革命性的望远镜
From a researcher's perspective, is Web evolutionary, or revolutionary?
每次你把一个全新的科技送入太空
Every time you put a new piece of technology into space,
或者用不同的方法观测宇宙
or you look at the universe with different eyes,
都能有一些革命性的发现 一些从未预料的结果
you … you learned something revolutionary, something that you couldn't have even predicted.
我不知道未来会有什么惊喜等着我们
I don't know what those surprises are going to be,
但这些技术都是革命性的 所以一定会有革命性的结果等待我们去发掘
but the technology is revolutionary, and there will be tremendous surprises that will astound us.
JWST已经登上欧空局的火箭 就差临门一射了
Web is on the doorstep, aboard a European Space Agency rocket.
包括Amy Lo在内的很多人
Some, including Amy Lo,
在望远镜长达一个月的部署过程中都会万分紧张的吧
they hold their breath as it unfolds itself on the month-long journey to its station around the sun.
大概六个来月后 第一张照片
The first images, in six months or so,
就会从红外波段转为可见的图片 登上头条
will be converted from invisible infrared into pictures suitable for headlines.
可能只有到那时 我们才能真正理解这背后的奇迹吧
Chances are what we see, we will not understand the very definition of wonder.